So, uh, forget those, you know, 300 page psychology manuals.
What if the secret to mental clarity is actually like hiding in the way a Jamaican
grandmother talks about a stray dog?
I love that.
Right.
Today, we are taking a deep dive into Donald Thompson's rich collection of
Jamaican Patois called Wood Fee Tea Day, which basically translates to word for
today.
Yeah.
And we're focusing purely on the mental clarity and wisdom category of his work.
I mean, the mission here is to figure out why these incredibly vibrant cultural
metaphors actually work.
Exactly.
Like how they act as cognitive shortcuts to a more peaceful, grounded life.
Well, because mastering the outside world requires mastering the internal
monologue first, you know, Thompson highlights this brilliant phrase.
It goes, if you, uh, think too much, your brain would bedaya.
Which means if you think too much, your brain will bother you.
Yeah.
And he pairs it with go easy and head.
We always keep clear and your heart not full.
So go easy and your head will keep clear and your heart won't be full.
It instantly makes me think of, uh, like a web browser with a hundred tabs open.
Oh, totally.
The spinning wheel of death.
Yes.
You try to process everything at once.
The fans start spinning and the entire system just freezes up.
Well, and that mental crash is a biological reality actually, because when
you overthink your brain's amygdala, uh, it can't tell the difference between a
real physical threat and an imagined scenario.
Wait, really?
It just reacts the same way.
Yeah.
It just dumps cortisol into your system.
But this Patois proverb acts as like a physiological circuit breaker.
By giving yourself permission to just go easy, you're actively powering
down that analytical panic mode.
That makes a lot of sense.
I mean, a clinical book tells you to practice mindfulness, which is super abstract.
But the image of your own brain physically bothering you, that gives your
mind a tangible reason to just step back.
That gives it a shape.
Yeah.
But getting your own mind quiet is really only half the battle.
Guarding that piece from the outside world is where, you know, our biology
usually betrays us.
Listen to this imagery.
Lion nay look back when mongrel dog bark.
That is such a powerful visual.
A lion doesn't look back when a mongrel dog barks.
And my absolute favorite extension of that is, uh, no worry when bad
mind judge, uh, cause mongrel dog bark off a people.
Basically, don't worry when bad minded people judge you because a mongrel
dog barks at people they don't know.
The mongrel dog metaphor is just brilliant because it tackles the
actual mechanics of ignoring critics.
Like think about a stray dog.
Why does it bark at a stranger?
Out of fear.
Right.
Exactly.
Fear and a lack of recognition.
Human critics operate the exact same way.
Jealous people attack what they just can't understand.
Right.
But I mean, saying be a lion sounds great in a coffee mug.
Human nature guarantees our blood pressure is going to spike
the second we feel judged.
So how does visualizing a stray dog actually bypass that
biological defense mechanism?
Because metaphors completely bypass the defensive analytical
part of the brain.
If a therapist just tells you to ignore the haters, your brain naturally argues back.
Yeah.
Trying to justify why the criticism hurts so much.
Right.
But when you visualize a frightened stray dog barking out of sheer ignorance,
you instantly reframe the insult.
It transforms from a personal threat into, well, a loud display
of the critic's own limitations.
Because you wouldn't get into a fast fight with a barking dog on the street.
Exactly.
The visualization strips away your biological need to defend yourself.
You stop taking the noise seriously, because you finally see
the source for what it really is.
And, you know, that shift in perspective changes how we
try to help other people too.
Oh, definitely.
We always want to protect the people we care about, but
Thompson includes this really tough reality check.
He says, no care how some people see the firelight, it
hasn't burned them via move.
Meaning it has to burn them for them to move.
Yeah.
It's like watching a friend date a walking red flag.
You point out the fire, you sound the alarm, but your warnings just evaporate.
Well, these proverbs point to a universally hard truth.
You know, you have to surrender the illusion of control over other people's choices.
You can point at the fire, but you can't feel the burn for them.
It's frustrating, but so true.
Yeah.
Painful experience is sometimes the only teacher that registers.
You also have to shift what you're paying attention to.
Like another profound phrase in this collection is sometime it good
fi listen with people.
Listen to what people do not say.
Yeah.
We get so caught up in the noise.
Like the phrase Demola look fi mistake and miss your message.
People look for mistakes and miss the actual message.
We focus on the words being shouted and just completely ignore the glaring
behavioral reality right in front of us.
Because silence, omissions, body language, these reveal true intentions far
better than spoken words ever could.
True social wisdom requires paying attention to the unsaid.
Rather than getting distracted by the volume, it just shows that Jamaican
Patois isn't just a colorful way to speak.
No, not at all.
It's a highly efficient operating system for navigating life.
It replaces dry clinical advice with these vivid living visuals.
We love to argue with advice, but you know, we intuitively understand a lion,
a barking dog, and a burning fire.
We really do.
And it leaves you with something to think about.
If silence and omissions truly speak louder than words, what is the unsaid
telling you in your own most difficult relationships right now?