if you want to know what kind of friend you are,
don't look at how you acted a dinner party.
Look at how you behave in your own living room
when you drop your keys at the front door,
let out that heavy sigh and think no one is watching.
- Because that is the real you.
- Exactly.
Today's deep dive is all about that exact kind
of raw, unfiltered connection.
We are pulling from a fascinating stack of notes
based on Donald Thompson's daily guide, Wood Feed Tea Day.
- Meaning word for today.
- Right, word for today.
And our mission is to unpack the incredibly rich,
colorful metaphors of Jamaican patois,
specifically focusing on the profound wisdom it offers
regarding family bonds and deep relationships.
- It's such a beautifully vivid language.
- It really is, it doesn't just translate words,
you know, it paints these highly relatable pictures.
Okay, let's unpack this.
- Yeah, let's do it.
- So, before we examine the friends we choose,
we have to start at the foundation of all relationships,
which is the family home.
- The absolute baseline.
- Right.
Thompson introduces this phrase,
"Picnay say, why him here, ayad."
Meaning, a child says what he hears at home.
- Which is just a perfect distillation
in child psychology, really.
- Oh, totally.
- We often think kids only learn the explicit lessons
we sit them down to teach,
but this captures how children are just a direct product
of their environment.
- Because they're always mimicking.
- Exactly, they are constantly mimicking
what they see and hear from parents.
The casual tones, the unspoken attitudes, and the yawn.
- It's like kids are little audio recorders left on
in the living room.
- Oh, that's a great way to put it.
- They don't just pick up the lessons,
they record the entire atmosphere.
But I have to ask, is this proverb
actually a subtle warning to parents
about their own behavior?
- Oh, it is an absolute warning.
It forces you to look at your underlying vibe,
like how do you handle a frustrating phone call?
- Or how you speak to your partner under stress.
- Right, because that is the exact blueprint
being programmed into your children.
- That makes so much sense.
But let's follow that thread outside the house.
If the home sets are baseline,
how do we use that to cultivate deep,
chosen bonds out in the world?
- Well, Thompson gives us two proverbs here.
- Yeah, and honestly they feel a bit contradictory to me.
- Let's hear them.
- First we have,
♪ You fee comin' like rosemary bush ♪
♪ People we glad feed around you ♪
- Meaning come in like a rosemary bush
so people enjoy your company.
- Okay, be an uplifting presence.
- Right, but then there's this other one.
Mon, we shared a problem with you.
We go, ah, deep with you.
Someone sharing problems builds profound friendship.
- Right, right.
- So here's where it gets really interesting.
Doesn't being a universally pleasant rosemary bush
directly conflict with the messy,
uncomfortable vulnerability required
to share problems and go deep?
- It definitely sounds like a contradiction on the surface.
But what's fascinating here is how they actually synthesize.
- Wait, really?
How?
- Well, think about the mechanism of trust.
People are inherently terrified of judgment.
- Yeah, for sure.
- So being that uplifting presence, the rosemary bush,
it isn't about putting on a fake front.
It actually creates the psychological safety necessary
for others to share their struggles.
- Ah, so the pleasantness isn't about avoiding conflict.
- No, not at all.
- It's a buffer.
You're creating an emotional airlock
where people feel safe enough to decompress
before they expose their actual mess.
- Precisely.
- If you cultivate a non-toxic environment,
you are building the safe container required
for someone else to finally drop their guard.
- That makes perfect sense.
But even with that safety,
you're still taking a risk when you open up.
How do you actually know
if that person was worth the investment?
- That's where Jamaican wisdom brings in
the ultimate test of durability, the metaphor of weather.
- Okay.
- The proverb compares the wet dauphrine
to the dry wet dauphrine.
True friends endure the storms, the wet weather,
while those only around for prosperous times,
the dry weather, are not real friends.
- So what does this all mean?
I mean, I love how this completely flips
our normal expectations.
- Yeah, it really does.
- Usually, wet weather is a ruined day.
It's something you complain about.
But in patois wisdom, the wet wet dauphrine
is the ultimate prize you want to hold onto.
- It ties right into boundary setting.
The source points out that an open enemy
is basically harmless compared to a fake friend.
- The ones who only show up when the sun is shining?
- Exactly. - Yeah.
- And that's why you shouldn't keep your door open
for people who lock theirs on you.
- Oh, wow, yeah.
You really have to protect your peace.
- Finding genuine people is hard.
When you find them, you protect that bond.
- It's such an incredible journey through these proverbs.
From the honest mimicry of the Yod,
all the way to the emotional shelter
provided by a wet wet dauphrine.
- There is so much wisdom there.
- It really is.
You have to cherish the genuine people in your life
because they are truly hard to find.
And it leaves us with this building thought to mull over.
- Let's hear it.
- If our children truly reflect the environment of our home,
what kind of weather are we preparing them to endure
and provide for others in their own future friendships?
Think about that the next time
you step through your own front door.