Are you ready to completely rethink
how you approach your daily grind?
Because today we are jumping into
a really fascinating deep dive.
- Yeah, it's definitely unique when we're looking
at the vibrant wisdom in Donald Thompson's word for today.
- Right, and the mission today is to really explore
these incredibly colorful Jamaican patois expressions
centered all around hard work and perseverance.
- We'll be verbalizing them, translating them,
and really unpacking how these timeless metaphors
perfectly apply to your modern workplace motivation.
- So let's just get right into it.
I'm gonna enthusiastically attempt to verbalize
this first patois phrase.
Let's see.
"Hod walk, bill, waddle, and dab.
"Dream make you sleep at a door."
- Okay, that was actually pretty good.
- Hey, I tried. - You did.
So to break down the English translation
for the listener here, it essentially means
hard work builds waddle and dab,
which is a traditional house,
while merely dreaming makes you sleep outdoors.
So action yields tangible security.
- I love that because it perfectly mirrors
so much of our modern hustle culture, you know?
It's like having this beautiful vision board
for your startup or your career trajectory.
- Yeah, all the big plans.
- Exactly, but you never actually do the daily grunt work,
and having a vision without that actual effort
literally leaves your career, well, sleeping outdoors.
- Oh, absolutely, but building that metaphorical house
is exhausting, which kind of naturally leads us to ask,
you know, how do you actually sustain the energy
to keep building day after day?
- Yeah, where does that internal fuel come from?
- Well, the next phrase answers that beautifully.
It goes, "Nobody know if you push you
"when you find you cal in."
- Meaning nobody has to push you
when you find your calling.
- Exactly, when you discover your life's true purpose,
that passion basically provides its own motivation.
You know, it eliminates the need for external pressure
from a boss or a manager.
- Okay, but I have to push back a little on that.
- Oh, sure.
- Like, does having a calling mean the work
is suddenly just easy?
Like, you never wanna quit 'cause you're just so passionate.
- No, definitely not.
And Thompson counters that exact idea with another proverb,
"Life beats you up when you step, cry."
- Life beats you up when you stop trying.
- You got it, because even with a calling,
if you give up, it leads to defeat.
You really have to trust yourself
and rely on faith and self-belief
to make sure you're on top all the time.
- Right, so it doesn't make the work painless,
it just gives you the drive to stick with it.
- Precisely.
- But, so you have this foundation,
you've tapped into that internal passion,
but what happens right at the grueling finish line
of a massive project?
- Oh, that breaking point.
- Exactly, and I'll share the final phrase for this.
"Adilas owns a strength teque ova di hill."
- It is the last ounce of strength
that takes you over the hill.
- The last ounce.
- Yeah, I mean, that perfectly represents
the reality of modern success.
Victory so often requires pushing through
when you are at your absolute most exhausted.
- Like when everything tells you to quit,
but you just have to give that final push.
- Right, persevering in that exact moment
is what actually gets you the win.
- So to wrap this all up,
the colorful, traditional wisdom of Jamaican petois
really provides this perfect, grounded roadmap
for modern career grit.
- Yeah, it really does.
You have to take action, find your internal drive,
and then push through the exhaustion.
- Exactly.
So we want to leave you with a question to mull over
regarding your own current work life.
- Always good to reflect.
- Look at your biggest goal right now.
Are you putting in that last ounce of strength
to get over the hill,
or are you just dreaming and risking sleeping outdoors?